JOE: It is not always obvious when
an individual with autism is going
to behave in a challenging manner,
but there are ways to help prevent
this happening and if it does happen
there are also ways to de-escalate the
situation or cope with the behaviour.
BETH: The first thing a person should do
in all situations is to remain calm so
that they can in turn calm the behaviour.
Being calm, gentle and patient and
giving an individual with autism space
can sometimes be all that is needed.
JOE: If an individual show signs of
behaviour that challenges it can be
good to find alternative activities or
objects to focus on to relieve the sensory
stimuli that may be affecting them.
BETH: Providing alternative objects
to play with, that provide a
similar sensory experience to that
provided by the behaviour, can help
to distract them and this can be
incorporated into their daily routine.
For a person who bites, this could be
to provide chewy tubes, gum, carrots,
raw pasta or sultanas, or for a person
pinches, they could be given playdough.
JOE: Opportunities for relaxation could
be created wherever possible, such
as watching bubble lamps, smelling
essential oils, as long as they are not
oversensitive to smells, listening to
music, or using a swing or rocking chair.
Distressed behaviour can be diffused by
an activity that releases energy like
punching a punch bag, bouncing on a
trampoline or running around the garden.
BETH: Reducing stressors by removing
distracting elements, going to a
less stressful place or providing a
calming activity or object, can help
to focus on returning to a calm state.
JOE: When supporting somebody who
is stressed, it is essential to
keep calm and quiet and to be a
consistent, safe presence to help
them feel they can begin to relax.
If this is not the case it may make
them feel less secure and more anxious.
Visual supports can be used to help
with de-escalating a situation.
BETH: It can also be helpful to
discuss the situation with the
individual once calm has been achieved
and try to teach them alternate
and more appropriate responses.
This should be done providing clear
directions and using simple language and
attempts by the individual with autism
to self-regulate should be praised.